Finding Aid for Palmer Family Architectural Drawings, 1950, 1963-1964, and 1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Palmer Family Architectural Drawings, 1950, 1963-1964 and 1980 1950
Palmer Family.
3 oversize folders
93790 Aa
Ann Arbor, Michigan family. Architectural drawings and renderings for their Ann Arbor, Michigan home designed by Frank Lloyd Wright and his associates.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection is on loan from William and Mary Palmer (Donor No. 7999 ) in 1991.
The collection is open to research.
William and Mary Palmer commissioned Frank Lloyd Wright to design a home on their property at 227 Orchard Hills Drive in Ann Arbor, Michigan. The plans were drawn up in 1950, construction began in 1951 and the house was completed in 1952. In 1963, the Palmers commissioned John Howe, head draftsman for Wright and one of the organizers of the Taliesin Association, to design a separate structure which was called a "Tea House" by Howe and the "Garden House" by the Palmers. The plans were completed in 1963, revised in 1964 and the structure completed in 1965.
The Palmer Family collection consists of three oversized folders located in the basement blueprint cabinet. The folders contain topological maps of the property, a complete set (10) of blueprints for the house, an oversized floor plan, blueprints of perforate block, hand-colored drawings of the garden plans and a colored house plan signed by Wright. The collection also contains the first rendering of the Tea House with two pages of revisions, furniture design details for the Tea House and an outside lantern.
Since coming to the library in 1992, photocopies and photographic copies have been made of some of the more fragile items in the collection. The researcher is encouraged to consult these before inquiring about access to the originals. The number in parentheses at the end of each description is an identifying number assigned by the donor for indiviudal drawings or a group of related drawings.
For an extensive selection of photographs of the Palmer house, the researcher should consult The Wright Style by Carla Lind (1992).
Subjects:
Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.
- Blueprints And Drawings
  - Topographic map, undated (Folder 1)
    (# 1)
  - Topographic drawing with paste-up of house done by client, undated (Folder 1)
    (# 2)
  - Blueprints of house, 1950 (Folder 1)
    (complete set of 10 with pencil notations)
    (# 3)
  - Blueline prints of house, 1950 (Folder 1)
    (complete set bound)
    (# 4)
  - Blueprint pages, nos. 2, 4, 5, 6, 9, 1950 (Folder 1)
    (# 5)
  - Blueprint, 1950 (Folder 2)
    (page 10 without pencil marks)
    (# 6)
  - Floor plan, undated (Folder 2)
    (# 7)
  - General house plan, undated (Folder 2)
    (tracing by client)
    (# 8)
  - General plan, sheet 3, undated (Folder 2)
    (partial copy, reverse printed)
    (# 9)
  - Blueprint of precast perforated block, 1950, 2 blueprints (Folder 2)
    (# 10)
  - Rug plan, undated, 2 blueprints and 1 whiteprint (Folder 2)
    (# 11)
  - Tea House plan, undated (Folder 3)
    (# 12)
  - Tea House plans (first renderings), undated (Folder 3)
    (# 14)
  - Blueprint for table and lantern, 1980 (Folder 3)
  - Furnishing details, 1963 (Folder 3)
  - Tea House, 1963 (Folder 3)
    (two sheets of revisions and one sheet of interior details)
    (# 15)
  - Garden plans, 1950 (Folder 3)
    (hand colored, one copy signed by Wright)
    (# 16)